[music]
Um, yep. I'm Bill Maxwell. I'm at Hobot
AI. We build a open-source uh MCP
management platform. And over the next
20 25 minutes or so, we're going to talk
about uh why agents and MCP are good and
what MCP
is and the basic primitives that you
probably aren't aware of that make for
an actual good development experience
with uh MCP.
So the reason you know we know coding
agents are good probably the best
pattern for agents right now the most
successful anyway right we are
definitely seeing value getting um
making progress with these agents and so
uh they primarily work on code and code
is typically part of a larger process
your software development life cycle and
so as you're trying to work with these
with your code it also would be nice to
be the work with your repositories, your
issues, your tickets, pull requests, uh
the pipeline, the build status, you just
really trying to understand kind of the
endto-end picture of what's going on in
your, you know, software delivery life
cycle. And so the reason the way you
need to do that is you need the ability
to connect to systems. And there's lots
of different ways that you can connect
to these systems. I mean, you have a
coding agent. So you can just tell it,
hey, connect to this system. here's some
API keys and have at it and it could
possibly write you a function for that.
Um, tool calling I think I heard you
know came out with OpenAI a long time
ago now and uh so you could do it that
way but really you want a repeatable
process and a way of interacting with
these systems so that it becomes
portable. you're not reduplicating
effort or basically every time you
switch coding agents or clients that you
have to rebuild this tooling and these
systems interactions with these other
systems. And so that's where uh model
context protocol comes in. Um, this is
MCP and it's really a system designed uh
to connect your LLM models and your
systems together so that you can
uh interact with uh all of these
different um
systems and capabilities. And so just
really the way to think about it is that
it's the USBC port uh for these
applications for connecting AI
applications to uh tools and data
structures and other systems within the
your ecosystem.
And so
at a high level uh there's really a few
parts to the MCP ecos um architecture
that you're looking at. So, you've got
an MCP host, which is probably uh your
AI application. That could be like a VS
Code. It could be your cloud. Uh it
could be just a regular chat client. Um
and within each of those, you define
these client connections to um your MCP
servers. And so really when you're
interacting with MCP, it's it's these
two pieces interacting together um that
really sort of bring out the whole
experience. And so if you have a really
great MCP server that doesn't have all
of the capabilities uh with a client
that doesn't have all the capabilities
to support all of the functions, then
you're sort of, you know, in a in a
weird space. So when we look at this,
we're going to look at sort of the two
sides of uh the MCP bits and where those
primitives are. And so server side,
you're looking primarily at tools, uh
prompts, and resources. And so those
capabilities are put into the the MCP
server as uh and as the developer of
that server. And then on the client side
you have uh capabilities like sampling
uh elicitations and roots. And so if
your client supports these capabilities
you can now start to get a much better
UX or experience design developer
experience or user experience around the
MCP kind of context that you're working
with.
And so each of these primitives really
shapes,
you know, how you how you're going to
interact with these systems. So having a
tool that just calls something that maps
to an API may or may not be useful.
These primitives give you the ability to
get feedback to interact with um
uh you know the confirm and actually
have safety and actually have the
ability to um work with these tools and
systems in a safe way because agents and
AI the models they don't always do the
same thing twice. So you want to give it
as much context information as possible
to make the right choice.
So, first let's dive into tools. This
is, I think, what most people believe uh
MCP is. Uh when you hear MCP server,
you're thinking tool calls. Uh I think
on Twitter, they fight that, you know,
we can do tool calls 100 different ways.
We don't need MCP. But really, this is
the action surface and probably the most
value uh oriented piece of the MCP
server that people really want is they
need that ability to be able to get um
uh information from something else and
put it in uh to the context so they can
continue working with it, build a
presentation. And so these tools in as
you're developing or evaluating an MCP
server, you're really looking for clear
tool names. uh you're looking for uh the
descriptions to be accurate. You're
looking for uh clear inputs so that you
understand what's going to happen. So
for instance, this get github issue uh
you takes an issue ID. It's very
self-explanatory. It's like I'm
conversing with you which means the
model has a better shot of actually
understanding that tool and its purpose.
And so really when you're evaluating or
building the uh the utility that you'll
actually be able to get from it um is is
largely dependent on how this is built.
So if the tool name is ambiguous like uh
you know doesn't necessarily say like
get github issue and you happen to have
just get issue and you're also using it
with a bit bucket or a gitlab MTP server
and sort of the same because your
enterprise does everything um then you
sort of end up in this thing the model
can get confused right because if you
say something casually get this issue it
may or may not know which system you're
actually talking about. Um, and so,
um, you also want these tools to be
somewhat focused on the intention piece.
So, I want to create an issue, right? I
don't want to have to go get all the
different pieces that I would need uh to
actually create that issue on the
backend system and being able to call
with the different uh tools.
And so
um yeah, so looking at it uh a little
bit higher level at you know a good
design versus a bad design uh we're
going to focus on the intention of the
user. So, add note to contact and it
takes a contact name and the note. Uh,
that's clear. The parameters are clear.
Um, it's mapping to exactly what I might
want and casually say in the
conversation, it's it's sticking with
kind of that userbased language. and a
bad design and depending on which CRM
system you've ever used um you know and
you map things directly to an API uh you
have these different tools that are like
get the contact ID get the record get
the note and depending on the model or
you know somewhere it needs to be
instructed to do this right like the in
order for the agent to actually succeed
um either the model needs to know the
CRM and that's what it needs to do which
is unlikely if you're doing something
with like a local model and possibly
even with the frontier models is is uh
you know not likely that it would be
able to guess this. So then as a user
you're stuck prompting it and saying
okay do this do this do this which is
not a great experience for you as an end
user using these servers and so
um yeah that is
a bad design.
The other thing, you know, once we get
past tools, the other capabilities that
we have to at our disposal, building and
evaluating MCP servers are prompts.
Prompts are pre-built templates on the
server side that give the user clues or
actions to interact with the server and
actually have a chance at succeeding in
um being able to get the agent to do
what it wants or just in a casual
conversation.
um you know this is what gives people
sort of the action and the ability to
actually use these servers.
And so when you're looking at this in
claude or different clients you have
these slash commands and you'll see that
um there's basically they're like forms
and so you know you have create issue.
It's going to take like a title and a
and a repository name. It'll figure that
out for you. And so again, it's the
natural language way of interacting with
and as long as your tool names are good,
like it should just kind of line up and
have things succeed.
Um, yeah, the other one is resources.
And so resources are pretty powerful and
you know, a cool capability. Uh
yesterday I did a workshop um on on
building a chess client uh or chess
agent and so with resources we can
actually use something called MCP UI and
return HTML documents that then get
rendered in the chat client. So then you
can create these rich UX experiences
with drag and drop test pieces and the
MCP servers managing the states in the
background. But a resource in terms of
MCP can be really any bit of data. uh
these bits of data are not passed
directly to the LLM. Um it's controlled
by the user and so the user decides
whether or not they want to be able to
pass that. Um tools can uh create and
return uh resources so you can get the
record. So if I added a customer, I can
get the customer record back as a
resource.
And so, you know, when you're looking at
your client and how this impacts your
experience as a developer um interacting
with this, you can see once you have
resources, they're typically presented
to you in like a file structure or a
directory structure along those lines.
Um, it lets you select them and pass
them to the model. And again, a lot of
this is on the idea that you want to
control and have some say in where your
information is going, where your
documents are going, um, and what's
going back and forth between the model.
Sorry. Um,
next, uh, sampling. So sampling is a
weirdly named uh capability, but what
this does is it enables
the tool to request the client run an AI
query. And so if you want to get a bunch
of records and ask for a summary as part
of the tool, it can do that. And what it
does is it sends that back to the client
where the client then um gets to decide
um
does this make sense? do I want to run
this? And so in an ideal situation, uh
you would have a human in the loop that
actually approves that request that it
says yes, please do this. Uh that you
get to pick the model, maybe limit the
tokens. Um but basically again giving
back control to the end user through the
client. Um but still having a mechanism
to actually have the server leverage all
the benefits of AI.
So, elicitations,
again, some of these names, they're all
low-level protocol type of names, but
basically, this is confirmations or ways
to gather information from the end user.
So, a tool can confirm that you want to
take an action. It can present like,
hey, if you want to do this, I'm missing
this bit of information. instead of
failing and going back out to the LLM,
it can just prompt the user and say,
"Hey, you know, fill out this missing
bit of information and if you're ready,
then we can confirm uh that that's, you
know, what you want to have done and
actually go ahead and do it."
And so again, the the practical side of
it becomes sort of the
uh I say delete a database. It says
without an elicitation it says okay and
it just deletes whatever database it
happens to think you meant with an
elicitation you can say delete a
database it could say okay I'm going to
delete the production database are you
sure and then you can confirm or deny so
it builds this safety mechanism into the
um into the experience uh that becomes
really u pretty pretty critical I think
to good design of your MCP servers and
tools. So, as you're looking at
different servers, you're going to
definitely want to consider that
roots. Um
this one is basically the client when it
comes up it can say you know here's the
directories to this that you have access
to the service server side and the
server can then when it's referencing
things can say you know I need to list
directories or list files in this
directory and make sure it's within that
route and so uh these are not a security
enforcement boundary uh these are just
simply suggestions to the MCP server
uh you know to help scope and give the
agent some context on where it's working
and how that could look. Um you
uh yeah so again in a nice client it
would autodiscocover uh it might ask you
to provide this information and so you
can list different file paths the
different directories um and then you
can also confirm like do you want it to
have access to slash no I don't um but
basically
uh this gives you a way to uh specify
that and So now if we can walk through
sort of an example of how all of this
kind of comes together because there's a
lot of different pieces. If you can
think like I want to create the GitHub
issue, right? You're going to hit the
slash command as the user and that's
going to pull up a list of prompts. And
so there's a prompt that says create
issue in repo with the following
description. And then you're going to
submit that to the chat. the model's
going to uh you know process that and
then it sees that it's got a tool that's
available to make a to create an issue.
So it does that the tool is well written
and you know you also notice that it
didn't have a title field and so based
on the uh description that the user is
given it's going to send a sampling
request to the LLM to the client and say
hey generate a title for this issue
right and so the user can either uh see
that as a prompt or confirm but
basically now a title has been generated
by the model and is now
um goes back to the tool and then the
tool says okay let's confirm with the
user that this is what they meant and
it's okay to actually create this and so
here they say do you want to create uh
you know this bug based on the title
that was generated and here's the repo
we'll just assume that the description
is going to go in exactly as it was and
then the user confirms and says yeah and
the tool creates the issue and the model
simply responds great issue 2 1 2 3 4
has been created in /reo.
So that's how you like this is a good
use case of like how all the pieces can
come together more than just a simple
tool call and a hope that it did the
right thing. Um, yeah.
So, just coming back to it now, looking
and picking a good MCP server or if
you're a developer of MCP servers and
you're trying to figure out how do I
make this MCP safe and build trust with
my end users, then you're going to want
to make sure that you go through and you
have clearly defined tools. The name of
the tool is probably one of the most
important things in order to get the
agent to successfully call it. If you
ever get bored, give it random tool
names with really great descriptions and
it'll still get super confused.
Um,
again, you don't want your user staring
at a blank screen. So, you're going to
want to have prompts. Uh, you're going
to want to use elicitations for any
action that's going to have a side
effect. You're going to want to make
sure that they are able to basically
confirm or deny that is uh what you
want. You don't also necessarily if it's
been kind of a long conversation, you
don't want to just have it fail out and
have the user have to go back and enter
all that information. So, if you can
elicit and say, "Hey, you know, I need
this last bit of data. Can you please
provide that to me?" Um, again, that's
that's what you're going to want to see
or have available to you. If you are
making use of roots, say you're working
with source code, you don't want it to
move beyond sort of the repository
direct the git repository directory
you're already in, then you're going to
want to make sure that's there. Um,
and again, when you're picking an MCP
server, you're developing an MCP server,
the we didn't touch too much on this,
but there's two types of protocols that
an MCP server can uh typically interacts
with. There's standard IO, and these are
typically run on your laptop. And so
those are going to be given uh probably
an API key if they're going to be
running and communicating with remote
systems. Um if you're going to do a
streamable HTTP that gives you the
ability to host it centrally, set up
OOTH so that people are logging in and
you have uh centralized control over
that. Um you know, it's just a
consideration on on what you're using
and and how you're using them
on the client side. Uh when you're using
MCP servers, there's tons and tons of
clients. There's different agents.
There's different frameworks, but the
things that you're going to want to make
sure is that it does support the
elicitations bits. You're going to want
to make sure um when you're using a
client, if the server is asking you for
a confirmation, that you're actually
getting it and putting you in the loop.
Um the sampling bits, if your tool MCP
server is going to use it, it is a nice
thing to have. Not all clients support
this. Uh, but definitely you're going to
want the ability to uh rate limit those
requests. You're going to want to make
sure that these things are um Whoa,
sorry.
That surprised me.
Right. Um, yeah. So,
yep.
So then just we didn't talk too much
about uh the security side of thing. I
kind of just assumed that we wanted the
MCP servers. But with this your MCP
server potentially introduces new
vectors, but you shouldn't forget uh
your, you know, old school security and
do the due diligence that you would for
any other open- source piece of software
that you're going to run or consume. Um,
when you're selecting these MCP servers,
you are going to want to typically use
trusted third parties that have built
this. Uh, if you can use the remote, um,
and it makes sense for you, then that
makes sense. So, you know, the GitHub
host one remotely, Lassie host one. Um,
you know, just depending on the tool
sets and if it's available, you're going
to want to inspect all the tool names,
uh, parameters and descriptions. just
you're basically looking to make sure
it's not trying to inject something
malicious into your code. Uh it's a
little bit time consuming in the
enterprise. If you are running MCP
servers and you need to scale that out
for your whole organization, you might
consider using an MCP gateway like OOTTO
for audit logging and other things.
There's other open source alternatives
like uh MCP jungle for instance. Um,
you're going to want to scan your tool
names and parameters continuously um, in
case over time there's code that changes
uh, as things evolve. Um, and you're
going to want to centralize uh,
authentication. Uh, that's definitely
something that becomes pretty important
when you're scaling up consuming your
MCP servers. and then filtering um the
ability to inspect and make sure that
tool calls aren't taking data and
sticking that uh sending that to
different places that you don't want it
to go.
So, thank you. Uh if you've got
questions, I'll be here for a bit and
also at the Obot booth.
>> Thank you so much. I I feel a deep sense
of shame. I've I've personally developed
an MCP server and now I feel absolutely
terrible I didn't see this talk
beforehand. So, uh this is wonderful.
Thank you so much. I really appreciate
it. Thank you.
[music]
>> [music]